<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spiritual guide of life Offered and tendered to all mankind, without respect of persons, age or sex, to direct their feet into the way of peace. Or the inward and spiritual grace of God exalted as man's only teacher. By A. R.</title>
            <author>Rigge, Ambrose, 1635?-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57309</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831987</idno>
  <idno type="VID">36454</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240906531</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220591</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831987</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831987e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57309)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2132:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spiritual guide of life Offered and tendered to all mankind, without respect of persons, age or sex, to direct their feet into the way of peace. Or the inward and spiritual grace of God exalted as man's only teacher. By A. R.</title>
                  <author>Rigge, Ambrose, 1635?-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: Ambrose Rigge. Reigate, this 30th of the 3d month, 1691.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36454:1"/>
            <head>THE SPIRITUAL <hi>Guide of Life,</hi> Offered and Tendered to all Mankind, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Respect of Persons, Age or Sex, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their Feet into the Way of Peace.</head>
            <head type="sub">Or the <hi>Inward</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Grace of God</hi> Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Man's only Teacher.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi>By</hi> A. R.</byline>
            <p>IT is the Universal Concern of all Mankind upon the face of the whole Earth, to seek those things which belong to their Eternal Peace, Happiness, Tranquility and Rest with God, when time in this World shall be no more; yet such are the Wiles and cunning Devices of the Serpent and Adversary of man's Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, [who prevailed with <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in the beginning to break God's covenant of Life made with them] that he prevails with the generallity of their Posterity at this day, to slight, disesteem and undervalue that which should bring their Salvation, and them to the knowledge of the Way thereunto, which is God's Inward and Spiritual Grace, which came to be manifested and known by the second <hi>Adam (i. e.)</hi> Christ Jesus, <hi>John</hi> 1.17. This is the Root,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36454:2"/>Substance and Life of all true Religion in the World, and without it none in the Earth; for God hath given it, to bring Salvation to the Ends thereof, and to be a perfect and sufficient Teacher to all mankind, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. This was the Saints Teacher in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel Administration which brought their Salvation, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. And till the Nations and People in general come to hear and learn of this <hi>Inward</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Teacher, they can never be taught to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ungodliness and worldly Lusts, nor to live Soberly and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously in this present World; this is the <hi>Christ</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> Spiritually manifested in mortal Flesh, to destroy the Works of the Devil, which who doth not hear, receive, follow and obey, can never receive power to become Servants or Sons of God; but remains all their days in the Gall of Bitterness, and Bond of Iniquity, heaping up Wrath against the Day of Wrath, and the Revelation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgments of God, and their Religion and Faith is vain and unprofitable.</p>
            <p>Thus Christ being manifested, becomes the Author of Eternal Salvation in all who believe, and is that great Mystery which hath been hid from our Fore-Fathers for many Generations, where he is received, heard and obeyed, he manifesteth his strength and power in the Soul greater than the power and strength of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and binds the strong man, who hath long kept the Heart of many, and casts him out, and sets up there his own Throne, and ruleth till he hath put all his Enemies under his Feet; and so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Hope of Glory to the people, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. And whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth not thus receive, hear and obey him, nor give up thus to be governed by him, cannot be his Disciples, nor receive power from him to become Sons or Servants of the Living God; but though they may profess his Name in Words, and make a fair shew in the Flesh of <hi>Christianity,</hi> yet the true Christian Life they are Strangers unto, and without God in the world, dead in Sins and Trespasses, and can never be raised out of the Grave of Corruption, but as they believe in, and wait for the manifestation of his Power, [which is only known and manifested by his inward Light and Grace] to work all their Works in them and for them; and thus must Man be made the workmanship of God, created again in Christ Jesus unto good Works, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.10. This is the New Creation, where man receives the Image of God <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, which was lost in the first <hi>Adam: For as the Body without the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36454:2"/>Spirit is dead, so Faith without Works is dead also,</hi> Jam. 2.17, 18, 19, 20. For by Works of Righteousness brought forth in man, by Christ God's Righteousness, is saving Faith known: And no man can have true Faith in Christ, who manifesteth not the Works of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness in his Conversation; for the Fruits and Effects of <hi>Saving Faith</hi> in man, is an Inward Righteousness and Holiness, whereby man's Heart, Soul and Spirit is sanctified to God, without which no man can see God. And man must follow him in the Works of his Righteousness, and learn of him, and bear his Cross, <hi>(viz.)</hi> not one of Gold, Silver, Wood or Stone, but that which Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies their beloved Lusts and Pleasures, without which they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wear his Crown. For though man by his own power cannot work his own Salvation, yet as he believes in and follows him whom God hath given for a Leader, <hi>Isa.</hi> 55.4. and a Commander to his People, he shall receive power from him to do whatsoever he commands him, and be saved by him from his Sin and Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; For his Name is called <hi>Jesus,</hi> because he saves his from their Sins, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21. And whosoever is not saved by him here from their Sins, can never be saved hereafter by him from the Wrath and Displeasure of Almighty God, and that Death which is the wages of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</p>
            <p>Now, the means which God hath appointed to bring his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all mankind, is his Inward and Spiritual Grace and Truth which came by Christ Jesus, <hi>John</hi> 1.17. This inward Teacher as all mankind comes to hear and obey, they through him will be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.8. This hath vertue and power in it to bring forth Righteousness in man, and to work out all Unrighteousness: It is like a little Leaven hid in the Meal which Christ spoke of, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.33. and will leaven the whole lump of mankind into Sincerity and Truth, if it be received and obeyed. This is the pretious Pearl hid in the Field, which is the World set in man's Heart, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 3.11. which the Wise digs deep there to find, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45, 46. and having found it, selleth and parteth with all his Lusts to purchase it; for no man can buy it but with the loss and denyal of all things contrary to it, Gold will not purchase it, and Silver is dross in comparison of it, the Price thereof is above <hi>Rubies;</hi> and therefore the Wise Man said, <hi>Buy the Truth, and selleth it not,</hi> Prov. 23.23. Rev. 3.18. And no man can truly say, <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his,</hi> but as he thus buys it, with the selling of all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36454:3"/>to it; This is an hard Saying to many, or the most part of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, especially the Rich, who have great Possessions, and many beloved Lusts and Pleasures to part withal, which are as dear and near as their right Hand or Eye: This made the Young man, which Christ spoke unto, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21, 22. to go away from him sorrowful, who had great Possessions, upon which the Son of Man said, <hi>That a Rich man should hardly enter into the Kingdom of God,</hi> vers. 23. And <hi>That it was easier for a Cammel to through the Eye of a Needle than for a Rich man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> vers. 24.</p>
            <p>Here is the Mystery of Godliness Revealed, which the natural man cannot see, nor perceive, for it is hid from the Wise &amp; Prudent of the World, and discovered &amp; revealed unto Babes &amp; Litle Ones: the great &amp; proud men of the world are too bigg to enter the strait Gate, and walk in the Narrow Way, the Preaching of the Cross of our Lord Jesus to them is foolishness, [and they cannot see the strait Gate] which the Apostles preached, and all the true Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Followers of Jesus Christ took up, who were Crucified to the World, and the world to them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</p>
            <p>Therefore lay aside all your Imaginary Crosses of Gold, Silver, Wood and Stone, they are of no value, neither is their any vertue in them to Crucifie one Lust that wars in your Members; yea, though you may carry them in your Bosoms, yet your beloved Lusts lie there also unmortified, which every day wars against the Souls, and so far prevails, that they bring forth Sin in Word and Deed, which bei<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g finisned, brings forth Death, <hi>James</hi> 1.15.</p>
            <p>The true Cross of Christ is the Power of God in all who believe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. and [having made Peace through the Blood of his Cross] by him to reconcile all things to himself; by him, I say, whether they be things in Earth, or things in Heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. that by which the Antient <hi>Christians</hi> were Crucified to the world, and the world to them, was the Cross of Christ Spiritually born, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. But since the <hi>Christian</hi> Life and Spirit hath been laid aside and quenched, the knowledge of this Cross hath been lost, and people have set up an Image of it, and are become Strangers and Enemies to the Cross of Christ, as the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pharisees</hi> were in the Gospel-day, being without God in the world.</p>
            <p>The knowledge of the Mystery of God's Salvation to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ki<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> upon the Earth, must be opened and manifested by the Gift of God, <hi>viz.</hi> by his Grace and Spirit, as it is received and obeyed:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36454:3"/>
               <hi>For as no man knows the things of a man, save the Spirit of a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him: Even so the Things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.11. With this Spirit within did the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> seek the Lord, <hi>Isa.</hi> 26.9. And with the Spirit of Truth within must all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind seek the Lord, if ever they find him and know his Work; for without it the knowledge of God's Salvation is, and for ever will be hid from the Wise and Prudent of the World. This was the <hi>Jews</hi> blindness, the resisting of the Spiritual Gift of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.51. who by their wicked hands Stoned <hi>Stephen</hi> to Death, though they held up the Temple-Worship, the Offerings and Sacrifices, yet by Resisting the Spirit of God in themselves, they became more blind then he who had an Unclean Spirit, who said to Christ, <hi>I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of God,</hi> Mark 1.23, 24. Mat. 8.29. Yea, the Devil confessed him to be the Son of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>The grand Cause of all the Error in the World, is in going from the Spirit of Truth within, the Comforter now sent, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the promise of Christ, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17, 26. This Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter being received, heard and obeyed, leadeth into all Truth, and is a perfect Guide appointed of God for all mankind, to bring to the knowledge of God's Salvation; and thus to know the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom he hath sent, is Eternal Life; and all knowledge short hereof, is Earthly and Carnal.</p>
            <p>This Christ within, the Hope of Glory, hath been as a Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hid from Ages and Generations, but Revealed in the Gospel-Day, <hi>Col.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.26, 27. And thus manifested to the <hi>Gentiles, Acts</hi> 13.47. that he might be <hi>God's Salvation to the Ends of the Earth;</hi> when the wife professing <hi>Jews</hi> rejected him in his outward Appearance in the Flesh, to whom he was first tendred. This Inward and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Appearance of the Christ of God in our day, the <hi>Chief Priests,</hi> and literal and worldly-wise <hi>professing Christians</hi> do oppose, and gainsay, and will not have him thus to rule in the Hearts and Consciences of his People; but call the true Light, which is his Life and Spiritual Appearance, <hi>John</hi> 1.4. <hi>A dark Lanthorn,</hi> and <hi>A Natural Conscience;</hi> and so make the Word and Commundment of none effect by their Traditional Religion, which is set up in the Will and Wit of Man, and do every day crucisie to themselves afresh the Lord of Glory, and put him to open shame; for every wicked Word and Deed is as a Spear to wound him.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36454:4"/>
            <p> And no man can be a true <hi>Christian,</hi> who is not Baptized into the Death of Christ, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. (viz.) dead to Sin, this is the true Spiritual Baptism, of which <hi>John's</hi> Baptism with Water was but a Figure, Type, and fore-runner; neither is he now a Gospel-<hi>Christian,</hi> who is one outward; neither is that Baptism, that is outward in the Flesh; but he is a true <hi>Christian,</hi> who is one inward, and the one Baptism is that of the Heart, and of the Spirit: For it is neither Baptism, nor unbaptism (as outward) avails any thing, but a new Creature, Created again in Christ Jesus unto good Works to live in them, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.10. This is <hi>Christia<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity</hi> in its Antient Glory and Purity, which is restored and witnessed by receiving, hearing, and obeying <hi>The Inward and Spiritual Grace of God which now brings Salvation,</hi> Tit. 2.11. Of which Water-Baptism is an Outward and Visible Sign, as it is declared in the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer</hi> now used in <hi>England,</hi> where they say, <hi>That the Inward and Spiritual Grace is a Death unto Sin, and a New Birth unto Righteousness,</hi> &amp;c. And till the Outward <hi>Christians</hi> come to hear and obey this Inward and Spiritual Grace, they cannot know nor witness God's Salvation; for all without it is but as a Shell and Shadow, and as Chaff to the Wheat.</p>
            <p>And as Christ's Appearance and Manifestation in the substance of the Gospel-Ministration is Inward and Spiritual, so is his Baptism, and so is his Supper, and all his Ordinances, and all who truly <hi>Eat his Flesh, and drink his Blood, dwell in him, and he in them,</hi> John 6.56. <hi>For it is the Spirit that Quickneth</hi> all who are made alive by him, <hi>the Flesh profiteth nothing,</hi> Vers. 63. <hi>The Words he spake were Spirit and Life,</hi> though mysteriously spoken, at which the <hi>Jews</hi> Murmured, and many of the <hi>Disciples</hi> were Offended, Vers. 52, 60, 61. and lookt on ward, as too many do in our Day, who neither discern his Flesh nor Blood, and so Ear and Drink their own Damnation: Though the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> ate <hi>Manna</hi> in the Wilderness that was rained down from Heaven every day, yet as it was outward, they dyed, <hi>John</hi> 6.49. Therefore it is not the outward Bread in the Gospel Dispensation, that nourishes the Soul to Eternal Life, but the <hi>Spiritual Manna,</hi> which is received by the indwelling of the Son of God in man, and man dwelling in him, Vers. 56, 57. And they who thus eat his Flesh, and drink his Blood, have Eternal Life, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he will raise them up at the last Day, Vers. 54. This is the Anti-type,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36454:4"/>or Mystery of all outward Types and Representations, even the Cup of the New Testament in his Blood, in all who spiritually receive it; for the outward Flesh, Bread and Cup profit nothing, as to Souls nourishment; it is the Spiritual, that giveth Life, the Bread and Cup thereof Nourisheth up to Eternal Life. Where Christ is come and risen in the Spirit, his spiritual Bread and Cup shews his Resurrection in the Soul; here those who are quickned and raised by him, live by every Word that proceedeth out of his Mouth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.4. And being thus made partakers of his Resurrection, over them the second Death hath no power: This was Represented by <hi>Moses</hi> lifting up the Serpent in the Wilderness, <hi>John</hi> 3.14. <hi>Numb.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.9. So must the Son of Man be lifted up in the Soul, that all who are bitten with the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Serpent, may look to him, and be healed: For though he was made a Sacrifice to God for the Sin of the whole World, that through his Life and Resurrection the whole World might be saved, yet hath no man part in him, or his Resurrection, who are not [in t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is World] washed from their Uncleanness by him: For the Purging which all true <hi>Christian Believers</hi> own, is by the Blood of Jesus Christ to cleanse them from their Sins, which none can have the benefit of, but those who walk in the Light, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.17. <hi>For if we say we have fellowship with God, and walk in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, we Lye, and do not the Truth,</hi> Vers. 6. <hi>But if we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, we have Fellowship one with another, and the Blood of Jesus Christ his Son Cleanseth us from all Sin.</hi> Here is the Covenant in which the Benefit, Virtue and Efficacy of the Blood of Jesus is known and witnessed to this day, and must be throughout all Generations: And therefore hath the true Light (or Grace of God) lighted every Man that cometh into the World, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. That all might Receive it, and walk in it, and so be made Living Witnesses of the Blood of Jesus Christ, to Cleanse them from their Sins: If the Sons and Daughters of Men were come this to know, they needed not to have imagined an outward <hi>Purgatory</hi> to cleanse People from their Sins, the Blood of Jesus thus known and witnessed is sufficient to sanctifie and make clean in Body, Soul and Spirit, all who walk in the Light; and thus would God's Salvation be known and manifested to the Ends of the Earth: For as the Lightening comes out of the East, and shines to the West, so is the shining of the Sun of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36454:5"/>in the Soul of Man: But till the Day dawn and Day-Star arise in the Heart, the glorious Sun of Righteousness with heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Wings can never be known to arise; and until this is known and witnessed all Preaching is vain, and Peoples Faith is vain, and they are still in their Sins, and can never be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his Resurrection, nor conformable to his Death, but lives and dyes in their Sins, and whither he goes they cannot come, <hi>John</hi> 8.21, 24.</p>
            <p>Therefore let all be warned, to take heed to the true Light and Inward Spiritual Grace of God, &amp; give up to the Teachings thereof, that an understanding from God they may receive, to know the Mysteries of the Kingdom of Righteousness, which are hid from the Wise and Prudent of the World, who are glorying in Brain-Study, Humane Arts and Literature, and Natural Acquirements in the will and wisdom of man; through these was divine Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom never conveyed unto any of the Sons of men: But true Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is the gift of God communicated to them who love and fear him, the Secrets of the Lord to such are daily manifested, and they want not the knowledge of the Mysteries of the Kingdom of Righteousness, but can declare to others what God hath done for their Souls, of what they have tasted and handled of the Word of Eternal Life, these are able Ministers of the New Testament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And till the Nations and People in general be turned unto, and receive the Gift of God, which he hath universally given to all mankind to profit withal, the opening of Eternal Life they can never see, neither can the way thereof be manifested or known by any thing short of it, neither can any man know Life by it till he is subjected to it, and spiritually Baptized by it into the Death of Christ, this is the true <hi>inward Christian,</hi> whose praise is not of men, but of God: For the true <hi>Christian Baptism</hi> is a Death unto Sin, and a New Birth unto Righteousness, and none are <hi>Christians</hi> indeed but who are so baptized; upon this account said the Son of God unto <hi>Nicodemus, Except a Man be born again, he cannot see the Kingdom of God,</hi> John 3.3. And again, <hi>Except tha<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a man be horn of Water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God,</hi> Vers. 5. The Spiritual Water, wherewith the Holy Ghost doth wash all true Believers, and bring them into newness of Life: for he is not a <hi>Christian</hi> that is one outward; neither is that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36454:5"/>Baptism, that is outward in the Flesh; but he is a <hi>Christian</hi> that is one inward, and Baptism is that of the Heart, and in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, this is the true Gospel-Ministration, the last and greatest that ever the World shall be visited withal: This hath a more Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Glory, than that which stood in Meats and Drinks, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ordinances and Commendments of men, and therefore was to Remain to all Generations, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>Now all you who are sate down in outward Visible Signs, and are slighting and neglecting the Substance thereof <hi>(viz.)</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and spiritual Grace which must bring your Salvation, the Enemy hath deceived you in keeping you from receiving, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and obeying it, your sufficient Teacher and bringer of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> And so you are ever learning, and can never come to the Knowledge of the Spirit of Truth in your selves, which is given of God to lead you into all Truth, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. The Comforter promised by Christ, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17. to abide for ever; this he said dwelt with his Disciples, and should be in them, Vers. 17. This Comforter, the <hi>Spirit of Truth</hi> is arisen in our day, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested in all true Believers for this purpose, to destroy the Works of the Devil.</p>
            <p>But Oh! let the outward <hi>Christians</hi> beware, lest they reject him in his Inward Appearance, as the outward <hi>Jews</hi> rejected him in his outward appearance; for if they wound and crucifie the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> and of <hi>Christ</hi> in themselves, they will be as guilty of his Blood, as were the <hi>Jews</hi> of old: What slighting, despising, nay, blaspheming against this <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>spiritual Appearance of Christ</hi> have the <hi>Nominal Christians</hi> been guilty of this forty Years? How have they Buffetted, Stoned and Imprisoned him in his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> for speaking through them? Nay, they have crucified him afresh, and put him to open shame by their Ungodly Deeds, and hard Speeches.</p>
            <p>Oh Lord! I pray thee open their Eyes, that they may see him, whom they have thus pierced with their sharp Spears, and let a day of Mourning and Lamentation come over them, as was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied of the House of <hi>David,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Jerusalem, Every Family apart, and their Wives apart,</hi> Zech. 12.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. He is indeed a Comforter to such Mourners now, but crys <hi>Wo</hi> to them who now laugh, as he did in the days of his Flesh to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pharisees, Luk.</hi> 6.25. For outward <hi>Christianity</hi> now,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36454:6"/>where the <hi>inward Life, Spirit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of Christ is not received and witnessed, is of no more value in the sight of God, then were the <hi>Jews</hi> Offerings and Sacrifices, when they were inwardly pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted: <hi>For it is the Sacrifice of a broken Heart, and contrite Spirit, which the Lord regards,</hi> Psal. 51.17. And the inward <hi>white Linnen,</hi> which is beautiful in his Eye, his <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Dughters</hi> are all glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.13. They hunger and thirst after an inward Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Righteousness of Faith, which saith, <hi>Go not forth,</hi> Mat. 24.26. Rom. 10.8. <hi>For the Word is nigh thee in thy Heart, and in thy Mouth, that thou mayst hear it, and do it.</hi> This was the <hi>Word of Faith</hi> which the true Gospel-Ministers preached, believed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and who doth not receive this <hi>inward Word,</hi> cannot know the <hi>Salvation</hi> of God, for it is the <hi>Ingrafted Word that is able to save the Soul,</hi> James 1.21. And till People come to hear and do this <hi>Word,</hi> their Buildings are upon the Sand, and will not stand in a <hi>Stormy Day;</hi> for true and saving Faith is obtained and received by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Word, in all who live and stand in it, without which no man can please God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. Thus the Antients received Faith, and walked in it, and did many valiant Acts, both in the time of the first and second Covenant, and had Victory over the World, yea, they were made more than Conquerors over Death, Hell and the Grave, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. and obtained a good Report, tho' they obtained not the Promises, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.39.</p>
            <p>And now this Testimony I must leave to the World, that God hath sent his good Spirit into the Hearts of the Children of men to be their Guide, Leader and Director in all things relating to his Kingdom; and upon the receiving and obeying, or resisting and disobeying this Spirit, stands man's eternal Felicity or Wo, or nothing short of it can give mankind the knowledge of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of God's Salvation; and all Knowledge without it, is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carnal, and can never give Life to the Soul.</p>
            <p>And therefore all you outside <hi>Christians,</hi> Professors and Prophane, who have taken up your Rest in an outward profession of God and Godliness, but live in the prophane Fashions, Cu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>toms and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities of the World, far beyond those you term <hi>Heathens,</hi> my oul is often bowed down for you, because you are all <hi>resisting the a pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God's Spirit,</hi> as did the <hi>Jews</hi> of Old; and through your <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Religion</hi> (which you have received by and from your darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and benighted Ancestors) you have made the Word and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36454:6"/>of God of none effect, and have wrought despight against the <hi>Spirit of Grace,</hi> and have sate down at ease in an outside invented <hi>form of Godliness,</hi> imitating some things which the holy men of <hi>God</hi> did in the days of Old, through the leading and dictates of <hi>God's Spirit;</hi> but this to you is but an Image or likeness of a thing in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and it may be said to you, as it was to <hi>Judah</hi> in the days of <hi>Isaiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Who hath required these things at your Hands?</hi> Isa. 1.12. Your set-Days and Fasts, your Morning and Evening Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices the Lord hath no regard unto, but saith at this day, as in days past, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Wash your Hearts from Wickedness, the Fountain is open, put away the Pride and Abominations of the Heathen out of your Houses and Hearts, and boast not your selves that you are not as other men, peradventure no common Drunkards, Swearers, nor Extortioners, nor Thieves, nor Murtherers, but that you pay the Tythe of all you possess, give Arms, and have often and frequent Family-Duties, and frequent the Church and its Ordinances,</hi> as you call them; All this and much more if you had it, will not give you Acceptance with God, while your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side is full of Rottenness and Corruption; this Righteousness ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not that of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees,</hi> but in many degrees short thereof: <hi>Arise, arise, this is not your Rest, because it is polluted,</hi> Mich. 2.10. And shake off your Night-Garments, be Afflicted and Mourn, and Weep, let your Laughter be turned into Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and your Joy into Heaviness; for the Lord is arisen to plead with all Flesh, by his Sword, and by Fire, and he will leave the Outward Court to be trodden down of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> for he is arisen in his Fury as a Man of War, and is disquieting the Nations with Wars and Commotions, and causing the Potsherds of the Earth to dash one another to pieces, that he may make way and room for his own Kingdom, Rule and Government in the Earth; and all who will not that he should Rule, he will slay by the Breath of his Mouth, and the Brightness of his Coming; For <hi>Babylon</hi> must fall among <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> even that which hath been builded up, (whereby to reach to Heaven) in the Will and Wisdom of man: for it is come in Remembrance before the Lord, and great will be the Fall thereof, her Merchants shall Lament to see her Destruction, when they shall not be able to relieve her. And the Scattered Flock of the House of <hi>Jacob</hi> God will gather into his own Fold <hi>(viz.)</hi> his Power, within
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36454:7"/>whose Wall is the Well of Life, where all the Sheep of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture drink, and here shall none be able to make them afraid, for the Power of God is that Universal Fold, into which the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of the Nations must be; all who gathers not into this Power are false Shepherds, and gathers to themselves for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Gain; But the Gathering of the People shall be to the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Israel's</hi> true Shepherd and Leader; so shall the Kingdoms of the World become the Kingdoms of God and his Son.</p>
            <p>This Testimony lay upon me to leave behind me to the World, not knowing how long my Days may be therein.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Reigate, <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 30th <hi>of the</hi> 3d <hi>Month,</hi> 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Ambrose Rigge.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>